Guide to the Howard E. Evans papers, 1943-2012
Evans, Howard E. papers, 1943-2012
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Howard E. Evans papers, 1943-2012
24-02-1870
Evans, Howard E. (Howard Edward), 1922-
59.3 cubic ft.
Correspondence, minutes, manuscripts, photographs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Material relating to publications; professional correspondence, ca.1950-2002; minutes and printed material on the Veterinary College, the University faculty, and the Board of Trustees. Also, Veterinary College grade books, 1891-1989, kept by Professors Hopkins, Miller, and Evans and scrapbooks, 1987-2012.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of veterinary anatomy. Dr. Howard Edward Evans (Cornell University Class of 1944) is an emeritus professor of anatomy at the Cornell University College of Veterinary Medicine.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Professional correspondence, ca.1950-2002; minutes and printed material on the Veterinary College, the University faculty, and the Board of Trustees. Also, Veterinary College grade books, 1891-1989, kept by Professors Hopkins, Miller, and Evans. Also, correspondence and other material relating to the publication of the various editions of Miller's Guide to the Dissection of the Dog and Miller's Anatomy of the Dog.
Panorama group photograph of Officer Candidate School, Class 35, Camp Lee, Virginia, 1944, which included Cornell, Michigan, and Texas R.O.T.C. units. With photocopy of photograph of Cornell R.O.T.C. Quartermaster Unit, 1942-43, Major E. K. Halbleib, QMC. "before leaving for active duty induction at Ft. Niagara," May 1943.
Scrapbooks compiled by Howard and Erika Evans, 1987-2012.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Evans, Howard E. (Howard Edward), 1922-; Cornell University College of Veterinary Medicine.; Cornell University--Faculty.; Cornell University. Board of Trustees.; Cornell University College of Veterinary Medicine--Faculty.
Titles:
Miller's Anatomy of the dog.; Miller's Guide to the dissection of the dog.
Subjects:
Veterinary anatomy--Study and teaching.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
One folder of material relating to Miller's Guide to the Dissection of the Dog and Miller's Anatomy of the Dog is restricted. Box 56 Folder 1 is restricted, as well.
SERIES LIST
This collection is not fully processed and is expecting future additions.
Series I. Biographical
Series II. Cornell University
Series III. College of Veterinary Medicine
Series IV. Community Activities
Series V. Teaching
Series VI. Writings
Series VII. General Correspondence
Series VIII. Photographs
Series IX. Conferences; Seminars
Series X. Research/Subject Files
China
Series XI. Other
CONTAINER LIST
- Unprocessed Material (Box 1-52)
- Series I. Biographical
  - Vita - 1990s, 1990-1999 (Box 53, Folder 1)
  - Biography, 1992-2002 (Box 55, Folder 1)
  - Trips Taken; Workshop; Paper presented at symposium, 1992,1994; 2005; 1975 (Box 55, Folder 3)
  - Biographical Information, 2004-2006 (Box 58, Folder 1)
  - Vitas, 1996-2004 (Box 58, Folder 2)
  - Vitas, 1996-2004 (Box 59, Folder 1)
  - Honorary Member of Japanese Association of Veterinary Anatomists - correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 56, Folder 17)
- Series II. Cornell University
  - Grant Proposals - Provosts' Council, 1998 (Box 53, Folder 7)
  - Cornell Cats Program (Box 53, Folder 15)
  - Entomaniacs (Entomology Department Club), 1998-2000 (Box 55, Folder 2)
  - Cornell Adult University - Arizona, 1994 (Box 56, Folder 16)
  - Cornell Adult University - Arizona, 1994 (Box 55, Folder 3)
  - Cornell Adult University - Hawaii, 1979-1984 (Box 55, Folder 4)
  - Cornell Adult University - Hawaii, 1985 (Box 55, Folder 5)
  - Cornell Adult University - Hawaii, 1986 (Box 55, Folder 6)
  - Cornell Adult University - Hawaii, 1991 (Box 55, Folder 7)
  - Cornell Adult University - Hawaii, 2001 (Box 55, Folder 8)
  - Cornell Adult University - Hawaii, 1983-2005 (Box 66, Folder 1-14)
  - Cornell Adult University - Madagascar, 1996 (Box 55, Folder 9)
  - Cornell Association of Professors Emeriti, 2000-2001 (Box 55, Folder 10)
  - Cornell Herpetological Society, 1996-2001 (Box 55, Folder 11)
  - Field Biology/Natural Areas, 1968-1994 (Box 55, Folder 12)
  - "Guns, Germs and steel" Discussion Group, 2001 (Box 55, Folder 13)
  - Hunter Rawlings, 1995 (Box 55, Folder 14)
  - University Lectures Committee, 2001-2002 (Box 55, Folder 15)
  - University Lectures Committee, 2001-2002 (Box 55, Folder 16)
  - University Lectures Committee, 2002-2003 (Box 55, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 55, Folder 18)
  - Cornell Adult University Tours, 1990-2005 (Box 59, Folder 2)
  - Cornell Adult University - South Africa, 1996 (Box 59, Folder 3)
  - Cornell Adult University - East Africa, 1997 (Box 59, Folder 4)
  - Shoals Marine Laboratory, 2005 (Box 59, Folder 5)
  - Cornell Adult University - general, 1990's (Box 66, Folder 15-16)
  - Natural History, 1999 (Box 66, Folder 17)
  - Natural History, 2000 (Box 66, Folder 18)
  - Cornell Adult University - summer files, 1985 (Box 66, Folder 19)
  - Vet College tours for Cornell Adult University, 2006 (Box 66, Folder 20)
  - Cornell Adult University seminars, study tours, safaris, etc, 2000-2001 (Box 66, Folder 21)
  - Dinosaurs, 1994 (Box 67, Folder 1)
  - How animals work, 1985 (Box 67, Folder 2)
  - Pacific Northwest, 1987 (Box 67, Folder 3)
  - Mohonk, 1973 (Box 67, Folder 4)
  - St. Croix, 1981-1982 (Box 67, Folder 5-9)
  - Galapagos, ca. 1990's-2000's (Box 67, Folder 10-18)
  - Sapelo Island, 1987-1992 (Box 67, Folder 19-22)
  - Papua New Guinea, 1993 (Box 67, Folder 23)
- Series III. College of Veterinary Medicine
  - Veterinary School Announcements, Flyers (1), 1990s (Box 53, Folder 9)
  - Veterinary School Announcements, Flyers (2), 1990s (Box 53, Folder 10)
  - Cummings and A. de Luhunta publication in Acta Neuropathologica, 1977 (Box 58, Folder 4)
  - Biomedical Sciences, 1999-2004 (Box 58, Folder 5)
  - Veterinary School Announcements, Flyers, 1998-2009 (Box 59, Folder 6)
  - Dept. of Anatomy - Correspondence, Memos (1), 1990-2004 (Box 59, Folder 7)
  - Dept. of Anatomy - Correspondence, Memos (2), 1990-2004 (Box 59, Folder 8)
  - Explorations in the Life Sciences, Fall 2005-August 2009 (Box 61, Folder 13)
  - Permits #3, 2000-2010 (Box 61, Folder 14)
- Series IV. Community Activities
  - Ithaca Science Center, 2000-2001 (Box 55, Folder 20)
  - Paleontological Research Institute, 1998-2005 (Box 58, Folder 6)
  - Paleontological Research Institute- Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 2006-2007 (Box 58, Folder 7)
- Series V. Teaching
  - Course - Literature of Natural History, 1990s (Box 53, Folder 11)
  - Course - Literature of Natural History, 1997 (Box 53, Folder 12)
  - Course - Literature of Natural History, 1998 (Box 53, Folder 13)
  - Course - Literature of Natural History, 1999 (Box 53, Folder 14)
  - Report - Review of the Biological Sciences and a Course by H. Evans - Vet Anatomy, 1982,1986 (Box 53, Folder 18)
  - Reference Sources, ca. 1953-1975 (Box 55, Folder 21)
  - Natural History and Its Literature - Vet Med 607, 2002 (Box 55, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous, 1990, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 23)
  - Environet, 1982-1991 (Box 58, Folder 8)
  - Environet, 1992 (Box 58, Folder 9)
  - Environet, 1993-1994 (Box 58, Folder 10)
  - Explorations, 2005-2007 (Box 58, Folder 11)
  - Explorations- "The Chicken and the Egg: A First-Hand Dissection Experience", 1997-2000 (Box 58, Folder 12)
  - Explorations- "The Chicken and the Egg: A First-Hand Dissection Experience", 2001-2004 (Box 58, Folder 13)
  - Beijing Veterinary College, 1987 (Box 59, Folder 20)
  - Visiting Professor - Grenada (Contains Slides), 2007 (Box 59, Folder 21)
- Series VI. Writings
  - Conference for Veterinarians - Speech, Correspondence, 1990 (Box 53, Folder 16)
  - Articles by Howard Evans - 1990s (Box 53, Folder 17)
  - Additional articles by Howard Evans, 1967-2004 (Box 56, Folder 15)
  - Talk Given by Howard Evans in Japan, 1997 (Box 53, Folder 19)
  - Trilobites of New York State, 2001 (Box 55, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 55, Folder 25)
  - Miller's Anatomy of the Dog, RESTRICTED
    - 1st Edition - Correspondence and Reviews, 1960-1967 (Box 55, Folder 26)
    - 2nd Edition - Reviews, 1979 (Box 55, Folder 27)
    - 2nd Edition - Correspondence, 1966-1984 (Box 55, Folder 28)
    - 1st and 2nd Editions - Dean Poppensiek's File on Legal Matters, 1960-1963 (Box 55, Folder 29)
    - 3rd Edition - Reviews and Miscellaneous, 1989-1994, 1997-1998 (Box 55, Folder 30)
    - 3rd Edition - Correspondence, 1980-1992 (Box 55, Folder 31)
    - 3rd Edition - Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 55, Folder 32)
    - 3rd Edition - Photographs (Box 55, Folder 33)
  - Miller's Guide to the Dissection of the Dog, RESTRICTED
    - 2nd Edition - Correspondence, 1968-1971 (Box 55, Folder 34)
    - 2nd Edition - Correspondence, 1972-1983 (Box 55, Folder 35)
    - 2nd Edition - Hawaii Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 55, Folder 36)
    - 2nd Edition - Robert Habel Edits, 1970 (Box 55, Folder 37)
    - 2nd Edition - Oversized, 1970 (Box 55, Folder 38)
    - 2nd Edition - Miscellaneous, 1967-1983 (Box 56, Folder 2)
    - 3rd Edition - Correspondence, 1985-1988 (Box 56, Folder 3)
    - 3rd Edition - Illustrations, 1987-1991 (Box 56, Folder 4)
    - 4th Edition, 1994-1995 (Box 56, Folder 5)
    - Spanish Edition, 1972-1991 (Box 56, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Reviews, 1977-1988 (Box 56, Folder 7)
    - 5th Edition - Illustrations and Revisions, 1993-1995 (Box 56, Folder 8)
    - 5th Edition - General, 1993-1999 (Box 56, Folder 9)
  - Contracts - RESTRICTED, 1960-1998 (Box 56, Folder 1)
  - Dog Guide- 6th Edition, 1993-2004 (Box 58, Folder 14)
  - Dog Guide- 6th Edition, 1993-2004 (Box 58, Folder 14)
  - Early Cornell Naturalists, 1992 (Box 59, Folder 22)
  - Brightman Slides from Talk Given in Louisville, KY, 1976 (Box 59, Folder 23)
  - Sheep Embryology - Illustrations (Box 59, Folder 24)
  - Sheep Embryology - Cardiovascular System, 1972 (Box 59, Folder 25)
  - Sheep Embryology - Nervous System, 1972 (Box 59, Folder 26)
  - Sheep Embryology, 1972-1980 (Box 59, Folder 27)
  - Anatomy of the Ferret (Box 60, Folder 1)
  - Anatomy of the Ferret, 1980s-1990s (Box 60, Folder 2)
  - Anatomy of the Ferret, 1990s (Box 60, Folder 3)
  - Anatomy of the Ferret - Slides (Box 60, Folder 4)
  - Ferrets - Publications (National Ferret Review) and Correspondence, 1980s (Box 60, Folder 5)
  - Dissection and Study of the Bird, 1987, 1992, 1994 (Box 60, Folder 6)
  - Evans and deLahunta Guide to the Dissection of the Dog- 6th Edition, 2003-2007 (Box 60, Folder 7)
  - Dog Book Plates (Box 60, Folder 8)
- Series VII. General Correspondence
  - A-L (1), 1998 (Box 53, Folder 2)
  - A-L (2), 1998 (Box 53, Folder 3)
  - M-Z (1), 1995-1998 (Box 53, Folder 4)
  - M-Z (2), 1995-1998 (Box 53, Folder 5)
  - M-Z (3), 1995-1998 (Box 53, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Faculty Minutes, 1998 (Box 53, Folder 8)
  - A, ca. 1996-2002 (Box 54, Folder 1)
  - B, ca. 1996-2002 (Box 54, Folder 2)
  - C, ca. 1996-2002 (Box 54, Folder 3)
  - D, ca. 1996-2002 (Box 54, Folder 4)
  - E-G, ca. 1996-2002 (Box 54, Folder 5)
  - H-K, ca. 1996-2002 (Box 54, Folder 6)
  - King, Anthony, 1994-2002 (Box 54, Folder 7)
  - L, ca. 1996-2002 (Box 54, Folder 8)
  - Loew, Franklin, 1998-2002 (Box 54, Folder 9)
  - M, ca. 1996-2002 (Box 54, Folder 10)
  - Maina, John, 1991-2000 (Box 54, Folder 11)
  - N-Q, ca. 1996-2002 (Box 54, Folder 12)
  - R-S, ca. 1996-2002 (Box 54, Folder 13)
  - Raney, Edward and Charlotte, 1985-2002 (Box 54, Folder 14)
  - T-V, ca. 1996-2002 (Box 54, Folder 15)
  - W, ca. 1996-2002 (Box 54, Folder 16)
  - X-Z, ca. 1996-2002 (Box 54, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1999-2001 (Box 54, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1999-2001 (Box 54, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1999-2001 (Box 54, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1999-2001 (Box 54, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence A-B, 2001-2006 (Box 58, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence C, 2001-2006 (Box 58, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence D-G, 2001-2007 (Box 58, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence H, 2001-2006 (Box 58, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence I-K, 2001-2006 (Box 58, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence L, 2001-2006 (Box 58, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence M-P, 2001-2006 (Box 58, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence R, 2001-2006 (Box 58, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence S-Z, 2001-2007 (Box 58, Folder 23)
  - Christmas Letter, 2005 & 2006 (Box 58, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence - Bryden, M. M., 1970-1972 (Box 60, Folder 12)
  - Materials Regarding Perry Gilbert Lecture, 1970s-2007 (Box 60, Folder 13)
  - Zoos - Correspondence, Memos, Publications, 1970s (Box 60, Folder 16)
  - Zoos - Correspondence, Memos, Publications, 1970s-1990 (Box 60, Folder 17)
  - Zoos - Correspondence, Memos, Publications, 1970s-1990 (Box 60, Folder 17)
  - Christmas Cards and Letters, 1993 (Box 60, Folder 20)
  - Get Well Cards and Letters, 1995 (Box 60, Folder 21)
  - Evans correspondence, 2003-2005; 2008 (Box 61, Folder 1)
  - Evans correspondence, 2010 (Box 61, Folder 2)
  - Evans correspondence #1, to 2011 (Box 61, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence #2: Dean Kotlikoff, R. Tarpley, Pres. Lehman, to 2011 (Box 61, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence #4: A and B, to 2011 (Box 61, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence #5: Braam Buizenhout: letters for woodchuck and appointment to faculty at Cornell from Nelly, 1993-1998 (Box 61, Folder 6)
  - C correspondence #6, to 2011 (Box 61, Folder 7)
  - D-G correspondence #7, to 2011 (Box 61, Folder 8)
  - H-L correspondence, to 2011 (Box 61, Folder 9)
  - M-R correspondence, to 2010 (Box 61, Folder 10)
  - Rhodes correspondence, to 2010 (Box 61, Folder 11)
  - S-Z correspondence, to 2010 (Box 61, Folder 12)
- Series VIII. Photographs
  - Skeletons (Box 56, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 56, Folder 11)
  - Panorama group photograph of Officer Candidate School, Class 35, Camp Lee, Virginia, 1944 (Mapcase-folder 1)
- Series IX. Conferences; Seminars
  - American Association of Veterinary Anatomists (AAVA), 1987-1998 (Box 59, Folder 10)
  - American Association of Veterinary Anatomists (AAVA), 1999-2002 (Box 59, Folder 11)
  - American Association of Veterinary Anatomists (AAVA), 2003-2007 (Box 59, Folder 12)
  - Conference - World Assocation of Veterinary Anatomists (WAVA), 1987-2003 (Box 59, Folder 13)
  - Scanned Photos - CDs - AAVA, WAVA (Box 59, Folder 14)
  - Conference - 5th International Congress of Vertebrate Morphology, 1997 (Box 59, Folder 15)
  - Conference - 7th International Congress of Vertebrate Morphology, 2004 (Box 59, Folder 16)
  - Seminars, 1956-1971 (Box 59, Folder 17)
  - Royal D. Suttkus Jubilee, 2000 (Box 59, Folder 18)
  - Workshop - Trinidad Trip, 1998 (Box 59, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 56, Folder 12)
- Series X. Research/Subject Files
  - Beagle Puppies - Shirley McCarthy, 1975 (Box 60, Folder 9)
  - Bull Pasture Pond, the Golf Course and Related Matters, 1980s-2007 (Box 60, Folder 10)
  - Formaldehyde - Research Files, 1980-2009 (Box 60, Folder 11)
  - Loch Ness Monster Papers - Including Presentation of the Loch Ness Monster Evidence, Bailey Hall, June 1976; and the Evans Hypothesis, 1970s (Box 60, Folder 14)
  - Taste Buds - Images, 1998 (Box 60, Folder 15)
  - China
    - Joint Work with Prof. Liu Jiwa of China on the Pancreatic Ducts of the Pekin Duck (1) (Includes Slides), 1992-1998 (Box 60, Folder 18)
    - Joint Work with Prof. Liu Jiwa of China on the Pancreatic Ducts of the Pekin Duck (2), 1992-1998 (Box 60, Folder 19)
- Series XI. Other
  - Zip disk of corrected copy of dog guide, 2003; ZD-2 (Box 56)
  - "In the Womb: Animals for National Geographic", 2006 (Box 56, Folder 13)
  - Slides (Box 56, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbooks, 1987-1996 (Box 62)
  - Scrapbooks, 1997-2003 (Box 63)
  - Scrapbooks, 2004-2010 (Box 64)
  - Scrapbooks, 2011-2012 (Box 65)